Wesley Roswell Coe Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
Wesley Roswell Coe Archives
1895-1930
IZAR.001692
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
5
The archives of Wesley Roswell Coe accumulated over his lifetime, notably including Yale teaching and research materials.
Coe, Wesley Roswell, 1869-1960
Biographical Sketch
A student of Addison E. Verrill, Wesley Roswell Coe (b. 1869, d. 1960) received his Ph.D. in zoology in 1895, and joined the faculty as an instructor a year later following post-graduate work in Europe. Coe's teaching career spanned 3 decades, and for 16 years he was Curator of Zoology at the Yale Peabody Museum.
Much of Coe's scientific research was devoted to the biology and taxonomy of ribbon worms (nemerteans); he wrote several important monographs on this group and described many new species. In 1899, Coe accompanied other prominent scientists to Alaska as a member of the famed Harriman Alaska Expedition. During the 2-month voyage, Coe collected a wide array of invertebrates that were later documented by himself and other zoologists (including A.E. Verrill and Katharine J. Bush, both of Yale University) in a series of large monographs.
After his retirement from Yale, Coe eventually moved to California and was affiliated with Scripps Institution of Oceanography as a research associate. For many years he continued to publish articles on a variety of topics dealing with bivalves and nemerteans. His last paper, a detailed account of bathypelagic nemerteans, was published in 1954.
Description of the Material
These papers include correspondence, manuscript related material, field notes, and biographical material.
Connecticut; Alaska; USA; California; Correspondence; Field notebooks; Manuscript materials; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- Correspondence, 1895-1930; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  These include correspondence with numerous researchers discussing systematics and zoology. Also included are correspondence from his day to day work as Curator.
  - John Hiram Gerould Correspondence. Correspondence from J.H. Gerould to W.R. Coe., 1906; 001694
    - John Hiram Gerould Correspondence. A letter from J.H. Gerould to Coe requesting a loan of a few specimens of Phascolosoma (Sipuncula) for comparison of specimens he has received from Woods Hole., 27 Sep 1906; 001695
  - Thomas H. Montgomery Jr. Correspondence. Correspondence from T.H. Montgomery to W.R. Coe., 1901; 001696
    - Thomas H. Montgomery Jr. Correspondence. A letter from T.H. Montgomery thanking Coe for his papers on the Alaska Nemerteans. He also asks if he could have a chance to examine Verrill's collection of Gordiacea (Nematophora)., 09 Apr 1901; 001697
- Manuscript Materials, 1895-1930; Series II
  - Nemertea., 1895-1930; 004606
- Research Materials, 1895-1930; Series III
  - Slide Box Annotations., 005699
    - Slide Box Annotations. Annotations transcribed verbatim from slide boxes. The numbers are reference numbers used for indexing only., 005700